ILGWU. Education Department. Fannia Cohn papers 5780/049
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Education Department. Fannia Cohn papers
1918-1962
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Cohn, Fannia M. (Fannia Mary), 1885-
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/049
6 cubic feet
6 linear ft.
Articles, reprints, pamphlets, correspondence, photographs.
The collection contains correspondence, subject files, speeches, articles, photographs, and programs from Fannia Cohn's term as Executive Secretary of the ILGWU Education Department.
3654771
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, June 05, 2012
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States, the ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. In 1995, the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE).
Biographical / Historical
Fannia Cohn, garment worker, labor organizer and educator, and officer of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. She was born in Minsk in the late 1880s (there is disagreement as to the exact year). Cohn emigrated to the U.S. in 1904 and began working in a New York garment factory in 1905. She joined the ILGWU in 1909 and quickly emerged as a skilled leader and organizer. She was the first woman vice-president of the ILGWU and in 1918 became Executive Secretary of the Education Department, a position she held until her retirement in 1961. Cohn played a significant role in worker education and was a co-founder of both the Workers' Education Bureau and the Brookwood Labor College. She died in 1962 in New York City.
Biographical / Historical
Local union's of the ILGWU established and maintained robust, ambitious educational departments early on in the international's history. As these groups grew in size and scope, the international office sought to coordinate and centralize educational programming for the union's members, culminating in the formation of the Educational Department in 1918.
The department's programming included courses at the Workers' University at the Washington Irving High School in New York City, lectures at Unity Centers and Unity Houses in the northeastern United States, and other events. The educational offerings of the International's Education Department were varied, as had been the education departments of the local unions, and included not only classes in labor studies but also courses in languages, music, and the arts. The ILGWU's 1937 musical "Pins and Needles" exemplified the diversity of the union's programs.
Directors of the Education Department, especially Fannia Cohn and Mark Starr, wrote extensively on the ILGWU's programs and worker education in general. Longtime director Gus Tyler not only directed the department, but also served as the ILGWU's on-staff scholar. In later years, the Education Department went beyond collaborating with other education organizations and arranging in-house programs to also supporting post-secondary education for union members and their families.
Scope and Contents
The Education Department records document activities across the entire period of the department's existence, with the bulk of the records covering the 1970s and 1990s. It contains papers from directors of the Education Department: Fannia Cohn, Mark Starr, Gus Tyler, and Kitty Krupat.
The earliest documentation of the department's work is found in the Fannia Cohn papers (5780/049, 5780/049 P); these contain correspondence, subject files, speeches, photographs, and printed material from her work as director of the Educational Department. A microfilm copy of the Fannia Cohn papers held at the New York Public Library (5998 mf) complements the Kheel Center's holdings. Documentation of the work of another longtime leader of the Education Department, Mark Starr, is contained in these records (5780/166, 5780/166 PUBS), as well as in a related collection from Starr on worker education programs (5243).
Documentation of the work of Gus Tyler, who led the merged Education and Political Department after Mark Starr's retirement in 1960, is also contained in the ILGWU records (5780/052, 5780/088, 5780/096). Tyler's papers are complemented by those of Assistant Director Jasper Peyton (5780/086) and Special Projects Coordinator Beverly Shulman (5780/106). These collections contain routine correspondence and memoranda, reports, materials relating to training institutes, seminars, and conferences, and printed material.
The papers of Kitty Krupat, who was serving as Education Director at the time of the ILGWU/ACTWU merger in 1995, constitute the entirety of Education Department records from the 1990s. They include correspondence, memoranda, reports, and financial records relating to the ILGWU's independent and collaborative education projects, including the Worker-Family Education Program, the Joint Union-University Committee on Labor Education, and the Consortium for Worker Education, as well as numerous trainings, conferences, and seminars. Also included in the files are materials from local unions and regional departments of the ILGWU, files on the Internationals' conventions, and reports to the General Executive Board.
The Fannia Cohn papers (5780/049) contain correspondence, subject files, speeches, articles, photographs, and programs from Fannia Cohn's term as Executive Secretary of the ILGWU Education Department. The materials in Series I are primarily letters between Cohn and various individuals pertaining to trade union matters in general and the ILGWU in particular. Included in the series are programs for lectures, concerts, museum visits and tours of New York City that were offered to ILGWU members and others as part of the Education Department's activities. Series II consists of bulletins, articles, lectures and course outlines. Most of these materials were written by Cohn herself or were prepared under her direction for use at the union's Unity Centers and at the Workers' University. A number of articles are by Mark Starr. There are also lectures by Charles A. Beard; Robert Brure; Babette Deutsch; Paul H. Douglas; Harry Laidler; A.J. Muste; Grace Scribner; Alexander Trachtenberg; Carl Van Doren; and Theresa Wolfson, among others. Significant individuals represented in the collection include David Dubinsky, Samuel Gompers, Morris Sigman ,Rose Pesotta, and H.G. Wells. Organizations include the Education Department of the ILGWU, the Brookwood Labor College, the AFL, Pioneer Youth of America, the Rand School of Social Science, and Unity House.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/106: ILGWU. Education Department. Beverly Shulman papers 5780/138: ILGWU. Education Department. Kitty Krupat papers 5780/166: ILGWU. Education Department records 5780/166 PUBS: ILGWU. Education Department publications 5780/086: ILGWU. Education Department. Jasper Peyton papers 5780/049 P: ILGWU. Education Department. Fannia Cohn photographs 5780/049 mf: ILGWU. Education Department. Fannia Cohn papers. Microfilm
Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Labor unions -- Officials and employees; Labor movement.; Labor movement -- United States; Labor unions; Labor unions -- United States; Labor unions and education -- United States; Working class -- Education -- United States; Articles.; Beard, Charles A.(Charles Austin), 1874-1948.; Brue`re, Robert W.(Robert Walter), 1876-1964.; Deutsch, Babette, 1895-; Douglas, Paul Howard, 1892-; Dubinsky, David, 1892-1982.; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924.; Laidler, Harry Wellington, 1884-1970.; Muste, Abraham John, 1885-1967.; Scribner, Grace, 1882-1922.; Sigman, Morris, 1880-1931.; Starr, Mark, 1894-; Trachtenberg, Alexander.; Van Doren, Carl, 1885-1950.; Wells, H. G.(Herbert George), 1866-1946.; Wolfson, Theresa, 1897-1972.; American Federation of Labor; Brookwood Labor College (Katonah, N.Y.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Educational Dept; Pioneer Youth of America; Rand School of Social Science
3654771
- A, 1921-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Agricultural Dept., U.S., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  I.c.w. Resettlement and Farm Security Administrations with Arch A. Mercey.
- American Federation of Labor, 1918-1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  I.c.w. Samuel Gompers & C. Thorne.
- American Labor Education Service, Inc. (formerly the Affiliated School for Workers), 1936-1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- B, 1921-1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Balabanoff, Angelica, 1938-1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Barnum, Gertz, 1913-1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Beard, Charles A., 1920-1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Beard, Mary, 1924-1928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Brameld, Theodore, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Brookwood Labor Colleges, 1921-1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- C, 1921-1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Chicago Joint, 1923-1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Education Committee, ILGWU, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Fannia Cohn to Julius Hochman (chairman) outlining educational activities of Union.
- Columbia University, 1926-1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  I. c. w. Harry J. Carman (dean) & William F. Russell.
- D, 1936-1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Panel Discussions, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Dubinsky, David, 1926-1950 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- E, 1922-1953 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Education, 1934-1945 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Incl. Liaison for International Education and Conference on the Educational and Cultural Organization of the United Nations.
- England, 1924-1954 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  I.c.w. The Labour Party, Ellen Wilkinson, Ernest Bevin and Morgan Phillips & ltr. from H.G. Wells.
- F, 1921-1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  I.c.w. Mollie Friedman.
- Form Letters, 1935-1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Forsberg, Allen B., 1922 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Frey, John P., 1922-1942 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Frish, Evelyn, 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- G, 1922-1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Greetings (Box 2, Folder 7)
- H, 1921-1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- History of the ILGWU, partial manuscript, no author, no date. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- I, 1939-1952 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Incl. Isaacs, Stanley M., 1939, 1943.
- J, 1921-1960 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Justice, 1937-1959 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Announcements of programs and related articles.
- K, 1926-1957 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- L, 1921-1957 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  I.c.w. Lewis Lorwin (Louis Levine).
- Labor Department, U.S., 1921-1953 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Life and Labor, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  (Publ. by Women's Trade Union League) Corres.
- Locals and Union Affiliates, 1922-1959 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Local 25, 1919-1925 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  I.c.w. Elsie Gluck (education dir.).
- Local 38, N.Y.C., 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Strike. Incl. corres. of the Citizens' Emergency Committee is behalf of the striking ladies' Tailors and custom dressmakers of the Fifth Avenue Shops.
- Local 91, N.Y.C. (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Local 178, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  May-June 1937, Education Dept. program.
- M, 1933-1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Miller (jr.), Spencer, 1926-1955 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous Items. (Union and non-Union) (Box 3, Folder 4)
- N, 1922-1958 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- O, 1946-1960 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Organization of American States. Pan American Union, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- P, 1922-1947 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  I.c.w. Rose Pesotta.
- Panel Discussions, General Matters (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Panel Discussions, 1942-1946 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Panel Discussions, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Panel Discussions, 1949-1952 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Panel Discussions, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Perlman, Selig, 1929-1959 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Pioneer Youth of America, 1926-1933 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Pioneer Youth of America, 1934-1938 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Pioneer Youth of America, 1939-1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Programs. Education programs from various locals. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Programs (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Education Department announcement of coming events and programs.
- Programs, 1940-1942 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Programs, 1943-1946 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Programs, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Programs, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Programs, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Programs, 1953-1961 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- R, 1921-1959 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Rand School of Social Science, 1930-1953 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Reports and articles on Education (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Rutgers University, 1941-1950 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- S, 1924-1959 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Sigman, Morris, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Strikes, 1924-1932 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- T, 1921-1959 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Training Institute, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- U, 1939-1954 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Unemployment Insurance, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- United Nations, 1949-1962 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  Visits of Union members to UN.
- United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organizations (UNESCO), 1945-1952 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Unity Centers, 1920-1922 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Unity House, 1921-1933 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  Incl. corres. re lectures held at Unity House.
- Unity House, 1937-1938 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- V, 1918-1953 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Wisconsin University at Madison, School for Workers, 1938-1959 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Wolfson, Theresa, 1922-1931 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Women's Trade Union League, 1921-1949 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  Workers' Defense League, 1921
- Workers Education Bureau of America, 1921-1943 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  Incl. corres., minutes and reports.
- Workers Education Bureau of America, 1943-1958 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Works Progress Administration. Federal Theatre Projects., 1936-1939 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Y-Z, 1943-1953 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- At Your Service, 1946-1949 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  Bulletin.
- Cohn, Fannia M. Notes for speeches, statements, articles and ltrs. [folder 1 of 6] (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Notes for speeches, statements, articles and ltrs. [folder 2 of 6] (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Notes for speeches, statements, articles and ltrs. [folder 3 of 6] (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Notes for speeches, statements, articles and ltrs. [folder 4 of 6] (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Notes for speeches, statements, articles and ltrs. [folder 5 of 6] (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Notes for speeches, statements, articles and ltrs. [folder 6 of 6] (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, A-C. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, D-I. (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, L. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, M-N. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, 0. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, P. (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, R-S. (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, T-U. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, W-WI. (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, WO-Z. [folder 1 of 2] (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, WO-Z. [folder 2 of 2] (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Convention speeches, 1937-1959 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- In Union There Is Strength (a play), 1937 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  One-act play by Fannia M. Cohn & Irwin Swerdlow, 3rd ed.
- Lecture Series, 1921-1925 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  Announcement of Courses given at Workers University.
- Lecture Series, 1921-1922 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  Attendance records.
- Lecture Series, 1921-1926 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Lecture Series. Ardzrooni, Leon and (Albrecht, Arthur E.). (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Lecture Series. Ayres, C.E. (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Lecture Series. Bauer, Marian. (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Lecture Series. Beard, Charles A. (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Lecture Series. Boone, Gladys. (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Lecture Series. Branham, Lucy. (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Lecture Series. Brissenden, Paul F. (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Lecture Series. Bruere, Robert. (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Lecture Series. Calhoun, A. W. (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Lecture Series. Carman, Harry J. [folder 1 of 2] (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Lecture Series. Carman, Harry J. [folder 2 of 2] (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Lecture Series. Carr, Michael. (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Lecture Series. Daniels, Margaret. (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Lecture Series. Deutsch, Babette. (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Lecture Series. Douglas, Paul H. (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Lecture Series. Fichandler, Alexander. (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Lecture Series. Gadsby, Margaret; Glassberg, Benjamin; Goodrich, Carter L. (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Lecture Series. Holloway, Emory. (Box 7, Folder 22)
- Lecture Series. Kennan, Ellen A. (Box 7, Folder 23)
- Lecture Series. Kopland, Sylvia. (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Lecture Series. Kornhauser, Arthur W. (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Lecture Series. Laidler, Harry W. (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Lecture Series. Lehrer, Leib. (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Lecture Series. Levin, Max. (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Lecture Series. Lieberman, Elias. (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Lecture Series. Lyon, John H. (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Lecture Series. Marx, Olga. (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Lecture Series. Mautner, B.H. (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Lecture Series. Melvin, F.J. (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Lecture Series. Meyers, J. (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Lecture Series. Miller (jr.), Spencer. (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Lecture Series. Muste, A.J. (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Lecture Series. Overstreet, Harry. (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Lecture Series. Saposs, David J. (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Lecture Series. Scribner, Grace. (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Lecture Series. Selikman, Benjamin; Soule, George. (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Lecture Series. Sherry, Harry. (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Lecture Series. Stair, Bird. (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Lecture Series. Stolberg, Benjamin. (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Lecture Series. Stopler, B.J.R. (Box 8, Folder 21)
- Lecture Series. Trachtenberg, Alexander. (Box 8, Folder 22)
- Lecture Series. Van Doren, Carl. (Box 8, Folder 23)
- Lecture Series. Weinzweig, Max. (Box 8, Folder 24)
- Lecture Series. Wilbert, A.L. (Box 8, Folder 25)
- Lecture Series. Wolfson, Theresa. (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Lecture Series. Wolman, Leo. (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Lecture Series. Zimand Savel. (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Lecture Series. Misc. course outlines. (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Lecture Series. Misc. course outlines. (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Lecture Series. Programs, 1920-1926 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- New Members' Classes. Lessons II and III. (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Officers Qualification Course, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  Syllabus for the six lessons.
- Plays, Union. (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Plays, Union. (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Printed Material from Education Dept. Misc. (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Printed Material from Education Dept. Misc. (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Reports of Education Department, 1922-1940 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Reports of Education Department, 1941-1956 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Songs. Union and local affiliates. (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Songs. Union and local affiliates. (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Songs. Union and local affiliates. (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Songs. Union and local affiliates. (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Starr, Mark, 1942-1943 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  Corres.
- Starr, Mark. Articles, arranged alphabetically by title, A-0. (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Starr, Mark. Articles, P-Z. (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Structure and government of the ILGWU, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  Article
- Studies. Union and Government Efforts to Regulate Wages and Hours in the Illinois Women's Cotton Garment Industry, 1939-1941 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  Garment Workers of Other Lands by Abe S. Weiss, 1941.
- Training-for-Trade-Union-Service, 1935-1941 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Training-For-Trade-Union-Service, 1946-1947 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Training-For-Trade-Union-Service, 1946-1947 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Trends and Prospects in the Women's Garment Industry, 1940-1956 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  GEB Reports to Convention.
- Workers' Education, 1926-1941 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  A quarterly journal of American Workers' Education.
- Workers Education Bureau of America, 1940-1953 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  Incl. newsletters.